Dennis Osafo

🔾 Evanston, Illinois, United States 🗷 dennis.osafo4@gmail.com 🔲 3146577723 🛅 https://www.linkedin.com/in/gribzdevo/

https://linktr.ee/gribblez_nation

SUMMARY

Experienced Data Engineer & Architect with 5+ years of expertise in managing clients, data/software engineering, analytics, network engineering, and system design with a consulting background. Proven record of successful projects and translating business requirements to provide technical solutions, applying for technical, delivery, or engineering positions.

EXPERIENCE

Data Engineer Consultant ACCENTURE, Chicago, IL

October 2021 - June 2023

KOCH INDUSTRIES, INC

- Developed, built, and managed metadata capture application for client's data lake in both AWS and Snowflake for XML and CSV raw data feeds from 7 different data sources.
- Improved client's data analytics capabilities by 80% through increased efficiency and accuracy of data capture processes by establishing automated pipelines for capturing metadata, scale database using AWS RDS, developing DML queries to efficiently capture metadata from the Glue Data Catalog and in Athena.
- Developed and presented front-end dashboard application to the client for displaying metadata data lake in AWS built using HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Flask, AWS Lambda, and Athena.

WALGREENS BOOTS ALLIANCE, INC

- Lead a team of associates to analyze 80+ Egress (outbound) feeds during an enterprise level cloud migration effort for the Walgreens Account. Developed DML and DBL queries to build databases and tables in SQL server and Snowflake data warehouses for cloud migration.
- Developed pipelines in Azure DevOps and Data Factory with Databricks, Python, and SQL to process 80+ on-premise egress (outbound) data feeds. Analyzed 100+ tables in Hadoop and Teradata to perform cloud migration to (dev, tst, uat, and prod) in Azure and Snowflake.
- Redeveloped Egress ETL infrastructure in Azure Data Factory by performing code reviews and lineage analysis to replicate 50+ SQL and Shell scripts, and on-premise ETL infrastructure built in Ab Initio and DataStage.
- Build reports and code base documentation to present to the client, essential for cloud migration to Azure and Snowflake on the analysis of on- premise egress outbound files, SQL and Shell scripts, and Java code base (servicing a front-end application).

SEMPRA ENERGY

- Developed, lead, and designed the entire ETL backend architecture using PySpark for 6 data sources utilizing AWS (Lambda, Glue, Quicksight, Athena, DynamoDB, SNS, SQS, S3) while managing two offshore backend developers to support development improving development time by 30%. Utilized terraform in Azure DevOps to automate AWS services for front end application in dev, tst, uat, prod.
- Performed incremental, unit, regression, API testing with Postman, test automation for ETL pipeline, and supported the development of front-end dashboard using ReactJS.
- Proactively communicated with the client to manage and track work activities in an agile environment: completing ad hoc tasks from project boards and resolving at least 6+ tickets for each sprint in the project lifecycle in Azure Dev Ops (ADO).

System Engineer

ORACLE CERNER, Kansas City, MO

August 2019 - October 2021

System Engineer (Data Architect)

- Onboarded 3 CMS and 10 Claims and Enrollment, and 2 EMR data sources and perform quality checks on data ingested in prod. Implement data pipelines and ETL processes for non-structured and structured data.
- Developed source validation and automated procedures for analyzing data by building Tableau dashboards and running SQL queries against 30+ onboarded sources. Deploy code for mapped data sources using modern DevOps and version control systems (GitLab, GitHub).
- Developed Python code to define programming logic for resolving file header issues in addition to running HIVE queries on multiple data source types (Payer and EMR).

Data Analyst

- Developed SQL scripts to query data in production, and performed quantitative analysis using Tableau for 20+ clients and their respective data sources (BCBS, AETNA, EMR.).
- Build workflows using JIRA to investigate and propose resolutions for data related issues for multiple clients.
- Lead troubleshooting walkthroughs, presentations, conduct meetings and communicate findings to multiple clients. Engineered and contributed to troubleshooting guides for Data Architects.

PROJECTS

Blockchain Platform

MetaTed Labs • August 2022 - Present

- Founder and full-stack developer building UI, backend and blockchain applications (smart contracts, NFTs, front-end, back-end architecture) for MetaTed Labs. Tech stack includes ReactJS, Nestjs, NodeJS, ThreeJs, MongoDB, and AWS.
- Develop and scale up our web applications, including our Play to Earn gaming experiences written in C# built with Unity, on the Solana blockchain. Collaborate with developers to improve development speed by up to 50%.

• Generate 1200 units of digital art to represent tokens on the blockchain to provide users access to our token-gated applications. Utilize digital assets by building e-commerce store with ReactJS and Shopify to transform into merchandise. Integrate 1 other blockchain to authenticate and authorize other users from other networks.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science in Information Technology Management

Minor in Computer Science • Saint Louis University • St. Louis, MO • 2019

CERTIFICATIONS

SQL (Intermediate)

HackerRank • 2023

Certified in how to perform data analytics with python.

Data Analytics with Python

Coursera • 2021

Certified in how to perform data analytics with python.

Google IT Support Professional Certificate - Technical Support Fundamentals

Google • 2021

Certified in understanding, and implementing information technology, like computer hardware, the Internet, computer software, troubleshooting, and customer service.

IBM - Network Security & Database Vulnerabilities

IRM • 2021

Certified in understanding the TCP/IP, OSI Models, DNS, DHCP, Switching and Routing concepts, and web sockets. Understanding vulnerabilities of key databases for cybersecurity including SQL, Couch, Oracle and MongoDB to building applications around those fields.

GCP Fundamentals

Google Cloud • 2020

Certified in building processes & applications using Google Cloud services.

COURSEWORK

NLP: Twitter Sentiment Analysis

Coursera • 2021 • Python Programming, AI/Machine Learning

Create a pipeline to remove stop-words, punctuation, and perform tokenization. Understand the theory and intuition behind Naive Bayes classifiers. Train a Naive Bayes Classifier and assess its performance.

Preparing Data for Machine Learning Models

Coursera • 2021 • Python Programming

Building an application that required extract data and select a region of interest and extract features from it so it will be represented as training, use several numpy functions, and label training dataset.

Google IT Automation - Using Python to Interact with the OS

2020 • Python and Bash Programming

Automation python script using regex to analyze syslogs and generate reports. Developed python scripts to produce reports of system information (date, uptime, memory, storage, CPU), perform code reviews, unit and integration testing.

Cloud Architecture with Google Cloud

2020 • Linux & Python Programming, Bash Scripting

Built a virtual machine instance and installed a simple web server using the command line in a Compute Engine instance. Utilize and learn GCP solutions - BigQuery, BigTable, Google Compute Engine, Google App Engine (GAE).

INVOLVEMENT

Operations Team Member

Saint Louis University • Campus Kitchen • May 2018 - May 2019

- Managed and performed the delivery of food to about 5 or more less developed communities and residences in the St. Louis metropolitan
- Distributed 100+ units of packaged food into containers ready for delivery as part of our responsibilities in the program.
- Collaborated with a team of volunteers to ensure delivery of food packages to 30+ apartment and housing units within safe areas.

SKILLS

Hybrid Cloud Engineering | IT & Engineering Support | Project Management | AWS | Terraform | Azure (DevOps, Data Factory, IaaS PaaS) |

GCP | MongoDB | Teradata | Apache Hadoop | Apache Kafka | Apache Spark | Hive | JIRA | Snowflake | Tableau | Power BI | Looker | R

PostgresSQL | MySQL | SQL Server | Python | PySpark | ReactJS | NodeJS | C++ | Java | HTML | CSS | Bash/Shell Scripting | Typescript |

Linux/UNIX System Administration | System Design | CI/CD Pipelines | SDLC | BDD Framework | Selenium | Cucumber.js | cypress.js |

DBMS | Oracle | DB2 | Databricks | Informatica | VMware ESx | vSphere | PowerShell | Windows Server